Finding Aid for Transplant and Health Policy Center (University of Michigan) records, 1986-1992
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Transplant and Health Policy Center (University of Michigan) records 1986-1992, 1987-1990
University of Michigan. Transplant and Health Policy Center.
3 linear feet
93836 Bimu 2
Multi-disciplinary center established to gather data by organ transplantation and to disseminate information to state and private health agencies, transplant programs, and other interested public organizations. The collection documents aspects of ethical and policy issues surrounding organ transplants. Series include education committee, ethics and social impact committee, liaison committee, and public policy committee.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group (Donor 8137 ) was received in 1992.
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
The record group is open to research.
The Transplant and Health Policy Center traces its origins back to 1984 when the Office of the Governor, the Michigan State Legislature, and the Michigan Department of Public Health discussed establishing a multi-disciplinary center to gather information needed to formulate public policy on organ transplantation. In 1985, the passage of Michigan Public Act 137 allowed the Michigan Department of Public Health to appropriate funds for and establish such a center, naming it the Transplant Policy Center. In 1989 the name was changed to Transplant and Health Policy Center. Although the center is considered a statewide agency, its director and paid staff have always been University of Michigan employees, reporting to the Vice Provost for Medical Affairs.
The Transplant and Health Policy Center collects and analyzes data pertaining to cost, psychological impact, and quality of life, as well as attitudes and outcomes related to organ transplantation. The gathered data is used to educate and advise state and private health agencies, transplant programs, and public organizations that are concerned with formulating public policy in this area. Within the Transplant and Health Policy Center there are six advisory committees: Public Policy, Ethics and Social Impact, Registry, Education, Liaison, and Scientific Reviews. The committees assist in the collection and analysis of information on transplants performed in the state; the cost effectiveness of various forms of transplantation; the psychological and social impact on recipients, donors, and their families; ethical issues; professional and public education related to organ transplantation; the development of quality assurance standards; and priorities for biomedical research. Committee members represent institutions, universities, government, professionals, and consumers throughout the state of Michigan that are concerned with organ transplantation.
In addition to providing education and advice, the Transplant and Health Policy Center has monies available for a limited number of research grants to individuals whose work addresses the goals of the center. The ultimate goal of the center is to become a model for a nationally cooperative network facilitating the exchange of information related to organ transplantation.
The Transplant and Health Policy Center, which is located at the University of Michigan Medical Center in Ann Arbor, is the first center in the United States created specifically for the study of public policy issues related to organ transplantation. Jeremiah G. Turcotte, M.D., transplant surgeon and professor, Department of Surgery at the University of Michigan Medical Center, has been director since inception of the center. Due to state budget cuts in the early 1990s, the staff of the center was reduced in size and its activities greatly curtailed. The advisory committees do meet, but only infrequently, and on an as needed basis.
The records of the Transplant and Health Policy Center document the work of the Education, Ethics and Social Impact, Liaison and Public Policy committees. The records span the years 1986-1992; the bulk of the materials cover 1987-1990. The records are divided into four series: Education Committee, Ethics and Social Impact Committee, Liaison Committee, and Public Policy Committee.
Subjects:
Donation of organs, tissues, etc.; Transplantation of organs, tissues, etc.; University of Michigan. Transplant and Health Policy Center.
- Education Committee 1986-1992
  The Education Committee series, (1.0 linear feet), Ethics and Social Impact Committee series (0.5 linear feet), Liaison Committee series (0.5 linear feet), and the Public Policy Committee series (1.0 linear feet) are all arranged in topical order and consist primarily of communications, handouts, and minutes. The "communications" files contain memos and outgoing and incoming mail that reflect the interests of the particular committee. The "handouts" files contain reference materials sent to committee members prior to a meeting. The reference materials consist of reprinted articles and reports collected from various sources that relate to the particular issues being studied by the committee. The "minutes/agenda" files contain agendas, minutes and action items. The researcher should look at the minutes and communications for any particular committee; together they provide a more complete picture of the work of each committee. The researcher should note that the "communications" folders sometimes contain stray minutes and handouts.
  The Education Committee works to increase awareness by the transplant patient, health care professional and general public of issues related to organ transplantation. Documented within its files are programs to educate the public, including the Driver's Education curriculum and a media campaign addressing the problem of low organ donation rates among the minority population of Detroit. Also documented is the need for a model curriculum for medical professionals and new standards for licensing and certification of health professionals.
  - Budget 1986 (Box 1)
  - Communications
    - 1986 (Box 1)
    - 1987 (Box 1)
    - 1988 (Box 1)
    - 1989 (Box 1)
    - 1990 (Box 1)
    - 1991-1992 (Box 1)
  - Grant Proposals 1986 (Box 1)
  - Handouts
    - 1988 (Box 1)
    - 1989 (Box 1)
    - 1990, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1991 (Box 1)
  - Michigan Comprehensive Health Curriculum 1987-1988 (Box 1)
  - Members
    - 1986-1987 (Box 1)
    - 1988 (Box 1)
    - 1989 (Box 1)
    - 1990-1991 (Box 1)
  - Minutes/Agendas
    - 1986 (Box 1)
    - 1987 (Box 1)
    - 1988 (Box 1)
    - 1989 (Box 1)
    - 1990 (Box 1)
    - 1991-1992 (Box 1)
  - Subcommittees
    - Professional Education 1988 (Box 1)
    - Public Education 1987-1988 (Box 1)
- Ethics and Social Impact Committee 1986-1992
  The Ethics and Social Impact Committee focuses on issues such as procurement, allocation, payment, clinical problems of organ transplantation, and social issues surrounding the patient, family, and the professional's view of organ transplantation. The files include the committee's response to the recommendation by the National Task Force on Organ Transplantation that donated organs be considered a national resource. Other materials of interest are those relating to patient selection criteria, the use of anencephalic infants as organ donors, and liver transplants for alcoholics.
  - Budget 1986-1988 (Box 2)
  - Communications
    - 1986-1987 (Box 2)
    - 1988 (Box 2)
    - 1989 (Box 2)
    - 1990 (Box 2)
    - 1991 (Box 2)
    - 1992 (Box 2)
  - Handouts 1991-1992 (Box 2)
  - Members 1986-1988 (Box 2)
  - Minutes/Agendas
    - 1986 (Box 2)
    - 1987 (Box 2)
    - 1988 (Box 2)
    - 1989 (Box 2)
    - 1990 (Box 2)
    - 1991 (Box 2)
    - 1992 (Box 2)
- Liaison Committee 1986-1991
  The Liaison Committee acts much like a steering committee and coordinates the activities of the other advisory committees. The committee members include the chairs of all committees in addition to members at large. Because of its work as coordinator, files from the Liaison Committee provide the best overall look at the work of the center. Of particular interest are the "Minutes/Agenda" files, which contain reports from each committee. In the "1986 minutes/agendas" folder for December, there is a listing of goals and objectives for each committee.
  - Budget 1986-1988 (Box 2)
  - Communications
    - 1986-1987 (Box 2)
    - 1988 (Box 2)
    - 1989 (Box 2)
    - 1990-1991 (Box 2)
  - Handouts
    - 1986 (Box 2)
    - 1987 (Box 2)
    - 1988 (Box 2)
    - 1989 (Box 2)
    - 1990-1991 (Box 2)
  - Members, 1986-87 (Box 2)
  - Minutes/Agendas
    - 1986 (Box 2)
    - 1987 (Box 2)
    - 1988 (Box 2)
    - 1989 (Box 2)
    - 1990 (Box 2)
    - 1991 (Box 2)
  - Research Grants 1986 (Box 2)
- Public Policy Committee 1984-1992
  The Public Policy Committee develops and recommends policies on organ transplantation to the state legislature, the Department of Public Health, and other public and private organizations and institutions. There is information in the files regarding insurance coverage of living kidney donors and Michigan's Required Request legislation. The legislation required all hospitals receiving Medicare and Medicaid dollars to have a written protocol ensuring that families were informed of the option of organ donation. Within the 1990 and 1991 "Communications" folders there are transplant statistics for the state and nation. Senate and House bills that relate to organ transplantation are also found in the series for this committee.
  - Budget 1986 (Box 3)
  - Communications
    - 1986 (Box 3)
    - 1987 (Box 3)
    - 1988 (Box 3)
    - 1989 (Box 3)
    - 1990 (Box 3)
    - 1991 (Box 3)
    - 1992 (Box 3)
  - Federal/State Legislation 1984-1987 (Box 3)
  - Handouts
    - 1988 (Box 3)
    - 1989 (Box 3)
    - 1990 (Box 3)
    - 1991 (Box 3)
  - Members 1986-1988 (Box 3)
  - Minutes/Agendas
    - 1986-1988 (Box 3)
    - 1989 (Box 3)
    - 1990 (Box 3)
    - 1990 (Box 3)
    - 1991 (Box 3)